Guide to the Donald Orth geological survey photograph collection, 1869-1876
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Donald Orth geological survey photograph collection
1869-1876
C0233
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
0.25 linear feet (1 box)
49 black and white copy photographs that document the exploration of the American West in the late 19th century.
Orth, Donald J.
Historical note
These photographs came from the United States Geological Society. A majority of the photographs were taken by William Henry Jackson and are of the West, especially of what would become Yellowstone National Park. There is a photograph of Ferdinand Vandiveer Hayden who hired William Henry Jackson to accompany him and others on Hayden's trips to document the West. Hayden was a geologist who was the head of the United States Geological and Geographic Survey of the Territories in the late 19th century. Hayden along with Jackson were integral in documenting the landscape of the West and helping establish Yellowstone National Park. There are also some photographs taken by John K. Hillers who was exploring the West, especially the Grand Canyon, with John Wesley Powell during the late 19th century. There are photographs of Fridtjof Nansen and his boat Fram which he used during his expedition to the Arctic during the late 19th century.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds many other photograph collections.
Scope and Content
49 black and white copy photographs that document the exploration of the American West in the late 19th century. The photographs appear to be reprints of the originals made in 1869-1874 except for the photographs of Niagara Falls and Washington D.C. that appear to be original. The collection is organized alphabetically mainly by state with three exceptions: Niagara Falls, Portraits and Unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically mainly by state with three exceptions: Niagara Falls, Portraits and Unknown.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Donald Orth to Special Collections and Archives on June 10, 2013.
Index Terms
Persons:
Hayden, F. V. (Ferdinand Vandeveer), 1829-1887; Jackson, William Henry, 1843-1942
Geographical Names:
Arizona--Photographs.; Colorado--Photographs.; Montana--Photographs.; New Mexico--Photographs.; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.)--Photographs.; Utah--Photographs.; Washington (D.C.)--Photographs.; Wyoming--Photographs.
Document Types:
Photographic prints.
Contents List
- Donald Orth geological survey photograph collection, 1869-1876
  - Arizona, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colorado, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Montana, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Niagara Falls, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portraits, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unknown, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Utah, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Washington D.C., circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wyoming, circa 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 5)